Emma France Ward Papers, 1922-1966
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Emma France Ward papers
1922-66
Ward, Emma F. (Emma France)
MS 170
2 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Public health specialist and personnel manager. The strength of this collection is its documentation of Ward's career as a woman government bureaucrat during a period in which governmental influence in the regulation of industry increased dramatically. It is also a rich source of information about women workers, especially those in the shipbuilding industry during the World War II period. Materials include correspondence; articles written by Ward about the health and safety of women workers; and publications devoted to women industrial workers' health and safety.
Emma France Ward, the daughter of Wilbur F. and Emma Albert Ward, was born in Baltimore in 1886. She graduated from Goucher College in 1909; later she received a degree in public health medicine from Johns Hopkins University, and engaged in further studies at the University of Wisconsin, Harvard University, and in Europe. Early in her career Ward did settlement work. In 1931 she was the official delegate from the U.S. Public Health Service and one of three American women out of 500 delegates to attend the 6th International Congress of Accidents and Industrial Diseases in Geneva. Her long government career included appointments with the U.S. Children's Bureau, the Bureau of Labor Statistics, and the Internal Revenue Service. During WWII Ward worked for the Maritime Commission as the officer in charge of women workers in shipyards. After the war she worked with the Brookings Institution in Washington until her retirement in 1958. She died of a stroke in Baltimore in 1963.
Papers include biographical information; personal and professional correspondence; articles written by Ward about the health and safety of women workers; and pamphlets, reprints, periodicals and other publications devoted to women industrial workers' health and safety, especially in shipyards. The strength of this collection is its documentation of Ward's career as a woman government bureaucrat during a period in which governmental influence in the regulation of industry increased dramatically. It is also a rich source of information about women workers, especially those in the shipbuilding industry, and especially during the World War II period.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Emma France Ward donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1955 to 1961.
Search Terms
Industrial safety--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Shipbuilding industry--Employees--History--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--Women--United States--Sources; Ward, Emma F. (Emma France); Women--Employment--United States--History--20th century; Women--Health and hygiene--History--20th century--Sources
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical materials
  - Biographical sketch and bookplate, 1923, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituary, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z, 1922-55 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photocopies of correspondence, 1922-55 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - to Margaret Storrs Grierson, 1955-60 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Application to the United Nations, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings and research
  - Accident prevention, 1926-43 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles by Emma Ward, 1923-30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Child labor, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Industrial health, 1925-45 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Shipbuilding
    - General, 1944-46 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - England, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Publications, 1943-45 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Women in industry, 1943-44 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Printed materials
  - Bournville Works Publications: pamphlets, 1927-29
    - Pension: Provident and Benevolent Funds (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Education in the Factory (Box 2)
    - Bournville Housing (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets loose in box:
    - A Study of Absenteeism Among Women, 1943
    - Two Studies on Hours of Work, 1928
    - Artificial Humidification in the Cotton Weaving Industry, 1927
    - The Assessment of Psychological Qualities by Verbal Methods, 1938
    - Inventory of the County and Town Archives of Maryland, 1939
    - The Family Status of Breadwinning Women, 1922
    - Negro Women in Industry, 1922
    - Health Problems of Women in Industry, 1921
    - Hours and Conditions of Work for Women in Industry in Virginia, 1920
    - The New Position of Women in American Industry, 1920
    - Women in Maryland Industries, 1922
    - Institute of Citizenship and Government, 1923
    - Skoda Works, 1929
  - Book: Away in a Manger by Jean Thoburn, 1942